二零一四年借款修訂條例草案二讀辯論，審議條例草案嘅委員會委員莫乃光議員。
就委員會嘅報告向本會發言，莫乃光議員。
主席，我講話喺陳偉龍議員，即係委員會主席，即係《房屋條例》2014年修訂草案，今日病假。修訂草案嘅目的係為咗修訂《房屋條例》，以適應房屋發出。
The purpose of the bill is to amend the loans ordinance to accommodate the issuance of Islamic bonds, that is sukuk, under the government bond programme. The bill's committee, of which I'm also a member, has held one meeting with the administration to discuss the bill. It has also invited written.
views from the public but received no submission. The Bills Committee notes that allowing Sukuk
issuance under the government bond programme will help diversify the financial products and services for the Hong Kong financial markets, further promote Islamic finance in Hong Kong through encouraging issuers to raise funds by issuing sukuk, and reinforce Hong Kong status as a major international
National finance financial centre and an asset management centre. The Bills Committee supports the bill in principle. I shall now turn to the major issues deliberated by the Bills Committee.
立法會委員會審查了需要修訂《房屋條例》，並研究了擬議修訂如何達成該法案的目的。
The administration explains that as asset transactions involved in sukuk may not be regarded as a borrowing in the prevailing context of the loans ordinance, it is necessary to amend the ordinance to encompass the situation in which the government shall be regarded as borrowing.
monies from the special purpose vehicle set up to effect the sukuk issuance. This will enable the funds so this will enable the funds so raised to be credited to the bond fund. It is also necessary to amend the bond fund resolution to allow payments to be made out of.
The bond fund for meeting the coupon and redemption payments to holders of sukuk issued under the government bond programme, as well as the expenses incurred in relation to the issuance of sukuk.
Furthermore, the bill also amends the Inland Revenues Ordinance to exempt coupon payments and disposal gains derived from the Sukuk issued in connection with the government bond programme to enjoy the same profits tax exemption. So, as that currently applicable to.
Those in relation to conventional bonds, as issuance of sukuk under the government bond programme may have implication on other types of bonds issued under the programme and the local bond market. The Bills Committee has sought information on the administration's considerations in launching.
蘇克，under the programme，the target.
investors and offering mechanisms involved, as well as the management of Sukuk proceeds.
Members of the bills committees noted that the administration will determine the timing and actual issuance size of sukuk under the government bond program with regard to the prevailing market conditions and needs. The preliminary thinking for the inaugural sukuk issue.
maybe in the size equivalent to around US dollars 500 million or more. The administration envisages that the investors of the inaugural Sukuk issuance would be institutional investors, as they are the major player in the global Sukuk market. The bills
委員會進一步notes that that depending on the market interest and developments, the administration may consider extending sukuk issuances under the government bonds programme to retail investors in the future.
As far as the offering mechanism is concerned, the administration may engage financial institutions and legal advisers in arranging the deal through a special purpose vehicle. On the management of Sukuk proceeds, the government, the administration advises that the that investment return for
The bond fund is calculated based on average annual rate of return of the exchange funds investment portfolios over the past six years, or the average annual yield of three-year exchange fund notes for the previous year, whichever is the higher.
the bills committee has expressed concern about the competitive the competitiveness of Hong Kong sukuk platform vis a vis those of other jurisdictions in attracting international sukuk issuers issuers and investors, given that the major
Islamic financial centres such as Malaysia have well developed sukuk market, and that Hong Kong lacks ties with the such Islamic communities. In response, the administration advises that the inland revenues and stamp duty legislation alternative.
bond schemes amendment ordinance 2013 passed by the council in July last year has enhanced Hong Kong's competitiveness in the development of a sukuk market by providing a comparable taxation framework for some common types of sukuk vis-a-vis conventional
Bond coupon coupled with the core competencies of Hong Kong's financial market, Hong Kong is now on a better footing to promote Islamic finance through encouraging issuers to raise funds by issuing sukuk. The administration considered that sukuk issuances under the government.
bond programme will signal to the markets that Hong Kong's legal, regulatory and taxation frameworks are now are well established to accommodate sukuk issuance. This will give further impetus to to other potential sukuk issuers to raise funds in Hong Kong, and inaugural sukuk issuances.
Originated by the Hong Kong government, with an excellent credit rating of AAA, will draw attention and interest in the global market and attract a new group of investors from the Middle East and other parts of the world to Hong Kong's financial platform.
In view of increasing competition from other financial centres in developing the Sukuk market and Islamic finance, the Bills Committee has stressed the need for the administration to make concerted efforts with relevant parties to promote Hong Kong's Sukuk platform, including increase.
Increasing exchanges with other financial centres to foster cooperation and to keep abreast of the latest developments in the global stock market. Moreover, members of the Bills Committee have urged the administration to ensure a sufficient supply of professional and market practitioners.
with expertise in sukuk issuance and Islamic finance, which is vital to the development of the sukuk market and Islamic finance in Hong Kong.
The administration has stressed that the strength of Hong Kong's bond market, including sukuk market and the listing platform, are among the key features in the promotional work targeting international investors. In recent years, the administration has been collaborating with the relevant parties such.
As the Hong Kong Economic Economic and Trade Offices and the market in promoting Hong Kong's stock
platform overseas and keeping a close contact with the industry to encourage them to issue sukuk in Hong Kong.
The administration assures the bill committee that it will continue to seize every possible opportunity to promote Hong Kong's bond market and its so-called platform when meeting the institutional investors, issuers and asset managers.
On the promotion of market awareness of Islamic finance, the administration has pointed out that the Hong Kong Monetary Authority has been in close collaboration with overseas central banks, international organisations and local industry bodies to offer training.
For market practitioners, over the past few years, the Hong Kong Monetary Authority has organised a series of Islamic finance seminars and workshops covering a wide range of topics. The Bills Committee notes that these activities have received enthusiastic market response.
And provided opportunities for Hong Kong market practitioners to interact with their overseas counterparts and exchange views on issues relating to Islamic finance and sukuk issuance. Regarding cooperation with major Islamic financial markets, the administration advises that.
The Hong Kong Monetary Authority has been maintaining a close partnership with key Islamic financial markets such as Malaysia and Dubai. Moreover, the Securities and Futures Commission has been working closely with its counterparts from major Islamic markets, including signing a memorandum of understanding.
與迪拜金融服務事務局在2008年就達成協議，就互惠合作、在能力建設及人力資本發展方面，以及伊斯蘭金融的推動及發展，展開合作。
given that the sukuk has more complex structure than conventional bonds, the bills committee considers it important that the administration will ensure a robust regulatory regime over sukuk issuers with a view to providing adequate
Protection for sukuk investors. The administration has assured the Bills Committee that, similar to other financial products, sukuk are subject to the prevailing regulatory regime in respect of product offering, marketing, disclosure and intermediaries.
requirements in accordance to the relevant provisions.
在《證券及期貨條例》和《公司條例》。這些包括對發售人提出要求，要向證券及期貨事務監察委員會申請批准發售任何宣傳、邀請或文件。
which is or contains an invitation to the public for to enter into or offer to enter into an agreement to acquire the relevant Sukuk products unless an exemption applies.
the bills committee notes that as institutional investors will be the target investors of sukuk issued under the government bond programme, certain exemptions under the securities and futures ordinance will apply.
Neither the bills committee nor the administration will propose committee stage amendments to the bill. The bills committee support resumption of the second reading debate on the bill. Thank you, Mr. President. And the following is the view on the matters relating to the bill.
Of which myself and the honourable Kelly Vlong share on the opportunities and a and the pressing need for promoting the Hong Kong bond market. Now, Hong Kong is a leading international financial centre with a stock exchange which ranked.
The top, which rank among the top in globally for funds raised from initial public offerings from two thousand and nine through two thousand and eleven. However, in order to stay competitive, Hong Kong needs to capitalise on other successful factors and take a holistic approach in promoting.
Our financial platform, developing the local bond market not only enriches the diversity of the financial products, but also but it is also a key component which meets the intrinsic need of institutional and retail investors. The majority of local investors have very little.
Very limited choice if they are looking for a long term investment instrument with stable return. It is therefore not surprising to see that the soaring property prices in recent years under a low interest rate environment. For those who cannot afford to buy properties, they probably have.
要投資 in more risky.
In riskier and more turbulent markets, such as the equity market, foreign exchange and commodity, or others such as the victims of the Lehman Brothers incident, and they will have, they would have tempted to invest in complicated structured products to earn a slightly higher.
yield and the normal time deposits. I also believe that a mature and liquid Hong Kong dollar bond market is crucial for stabilising and sustaining investment futures for investment returns for Hong Kong's retirement population. A sizeable Hong Kong dollar denominated debt.
securities market can offer more options for MPF funds and bonds issued by local reputable institutions in particular will help provide employers and employees with relatively low fee alternatives and earn reasonably stable returns while enjoying the compound interest benefit.
Of course, those with more aggressive risk appetite may always choose MPF funds with higher risk, higher returns and higher management fees, like stock funds. The government should encourage and facilitate the provision of a more risk balanced choice of funds, and the rest will be market driven.
Indeed, Mr. President, Hong Kong does not lack competitive advantages required for deepening and broadening the local fixed income market. We have a sophisticated business infrastructure and transparent regulatory environment, a AAA credit rating status.
S and P long term credit rating, which can minimise the cost of the government's statutory bodies and government owned corporations for fundraising through issuance of securities papers. Unfortunately, the government fails to perform its roles in promoting Hong Kong dollar debt issuance. Based on FST.
統計局統計，政府、立法會、立法會及政府擁有的公司，發行了654個發行，總額約為港幣264.2億的港幣債券。
Securities between two thousand and three and and two thousand and twelve, or thirteen point two per cent of the total Hong Kong dollar debt securities issued in the same period, excluding exchange fund bills and notes (EFBs) issued by the HKMA, compared with other international financial.
中心，香港是落後於在發行規模上。或許有人會説，我們龐大的儲備證實了政府保守的立場，但我恐怕這有點短視，因為香港政府將投資港幣340億在大型項目。
Including a new airport runway, new development areas and reclamation in the coming years, it is high time for the government to leverage this golden opportunity to spend to speed up the development of Hong Kong dollar bond market as an alternative financial channel, rather than to.
be over-reliant on public revenues alone. This is particularly true when the government is subject to a financial commitment to address the need of the poor and our ageing population. To achieve this, we need a number of positive actions. First, the active participation of the government.
Legislative bodies and government-owned corporations in using the Hong Kong dollar bond instruments to raise funds for these mega projects where possible. Second, expedite necessary enhancement on regulatory and infrastructural supports to improve market liquidity. For example, in
Enforcement of underwriters' market making responsibilities, setting up of an electronic platform for online retail trading, and provision of a central depository system for Hong Kong dollar bonds, and third, promote investor awareness and demand through education programme.
發展 of the sukuk market or人民幣bond market should not be hindering the growth of the Hong Kong dollar bond market. Instead, we should head for diversity, which will make the bond market as a whole fly in Hong Kong. Together, the different types of bonds will attract a critical mass of
fixed-income traders, buyers and issuers, which will support the healthy growth of the instrument. I would urge the government to take up its pivotal role in accelerating the development of the Hong Kong dollar debt market, with a view to achieving a more diversified and resilient financial sector.
喺香港，謝謝，主席。李慧瓊議員。
主席，我代表民建聯發言，支持本條例草案容許喺政府債券計劃下發行伊斯蘭債券，以促進本地債券市場嘅進一步同埋持續發展。金融服務業係香港嘅主要經濟支柱，喺二零一一年，金融業對香港本地生產總值直接貢獻為三千零。
七十億港元，佔本地生產總值嘅十六點一個percent，是僅次於。
物貿同埋物流同埋貿易第二大行業，而金融業亦都係推動香港經濟增長嘅火車頭。喺二零零一年至二零一一年十年間，增長率為七點一個percent，比起整體經濟嘅增長率咧係超過咗嘅。雖然係噉樣講，但係香港呢一個。
國際金融中心咧，主席比起其他地方發展咧，係不夠全面。
股票市場咧過去乘住國企嚟香港上市嘅浪潮咧發展勢頭一直都非常好嘅，但係其他包括外匯市場、債券市場同埋商品交易咧，比起東京、新加坡發展得就比較慢。香港嘅金融業發展不均衡，最明顯嘅缺點咧就係抗逆能力較弱，一旦股票市
有啲咩風吹草動，香港經濟下滑嘅程度會可能。
被放大。
另外，外匯市場、債券市場同埋商品市場。
未能夠有誒。
有規模嘅形成咧，亦都係令到香港咧未能夠有充分嘅準備去配合國家嘅高速發展。港交所行政總裁李小加咧喺今年初嘅亞洲金融論壇上咧，都係指出喺過去三十年海外資金咧係透過貿易、外商直接投資同埋離岸資本市場。
三個方式經過香港進入內地，但係現在係內地有大量資金要走出去，而香港喺呢方面咧未準備好。佢警告：，如果香港保持現狀，不向多元化嘅市場發展咧，好快咧就會被邊緣化。金融發金融發展局咧，亦都有差唔多嘅睇法。根據金花。
法局喺去年十一月中公佈嘅研究報告，認為本港嘅金融產品同埋市場發展要開拓，要多元化。除咗債券、外匯同埋商品，仲要深化發展企業財資、房地產投資信託基金同埋風險管理等領域，以提升金融業嘅整體。
競爭力，所以為咗進一步鞏固香港國際金融中心嘅地位，發展債券市場係必須要走嘅一步。喺呢個背景底下咧，民建聯係支持本條例草案，容許喺政府債券計劃下發行伊斯蘭債券，亦都喺上年七月十號支持二零一三年税務及人化。
加税法例、另類債券計劃修訂條例，為幾種常見嘅伊斯蘭債券提供一個與傳統債券相若嘅税務框架，以掃除發展伊斯蘭債券嘅最大障礙。
主席，香港嘅債券市場仍然處於發展階段。根據金發局嘅資料，香港已經發行嘅債券。
證券餘額咧達到二千六百一十億美元，但係流通性就係遠遠唔及美國同埋日本。香港嘅債券發展未如人意，未如人意咧，主要都有幾個侷限，令到唔少公司冇選擇啊債券作為集資工具。首先，政府嘅發債有限，對於希望
籌集港元資金嘅企業嚟講咧，市場上咧並冇可靠嘅誒港元債券收益率曲線可供發行人參考，加上咧轉換為港元嘅成本比較高，窒礙咗為此而發行美元債券嘅業務。另外，缺乏信用評級同埋有關嘅專業知識，亦都不利於。
區內同埋本地公司債券嘅投資活動。
至於本條例草案提及伊斯蘭債券挑戰，亦都更大。首先，馬來西亞等其他主要嘅伊斯蘭金融中心，伊斯蘭債券市場發展已經成熟。另外，香港與伊斯蘭社羣亦都缺乏聯繫，所以咧，本會同時先至一再誒希望政府啊，香港嘅計。
繼續努力，同埋其他嘅司法管轄區咧一齊努力咧，去推動香港作為伊斯蘭債券嘅一個重要嘅平台，為咗進一步推動本地伊斯蘭。
金融嘅發展，民建聯咧支持利用政府債券計劃作為發展契機，但係與此同時咧，我哋都促促請政府要把握每個機會，向海外推廣香港伊斯蘭債券嘅平台，並與業界保持緊密嘅聯繫，鼓勵佢哋喺香港發行伊斯蘭債券。另外咧，有充足嘅人才供應。
對發展香港伊斯蘭債券市場亦都非常重要。政府當局要同海外組織同埋本地業界組織咧，係緊密合作，為市場提供培訓，在結合香港金融市場嘅核心優勢。
包括監管。
機構誒嘅透明度、税率簡單、誒偏低、國際金融中心、中介雲集等等呢啲嘅誒市場基建嘅設施，先至可以令香港更有條件咁透過發行債券。
誒發行。
鼓勵發債人發行伊斯蘭債券咧，籌集資金，從而推動誒伊斯蘭金融債券嘅發展。主席，我過去都見到局長其實喺誒推動誒本港金融市場嘅多元化方面做咗誒不同嘅工作。噉啊，希望局方繼續努力啊，為誒香港金融市場嘅多元化咧而誒再。
再行前一步，主席本人僅此陳辭。有冇其他議員要發言？
如果冇咧，就請財經事務及庫務局局長發言答辯。
主席，首先我哋感謝法案委員會主席梁繼昌議員、其他議員、立法會秘書處以及法律顧問所付出嘅努力，令到審議二零一四年借款。
修訂條例草案，下簡稱誒條例草案嘅工作咧，得以順利完成。
我哋要感謝議員支持條例草案喺今日恢復二讀辯論。
本條例草案主要目的係修訂借款條例，使政府債券計劃可發行伊斯蘭債券。
政府一直係透過進行政府債券計劃，盡力致力為香港資本市場提供更多種類嘅債券。
擴大投資者層面，從而促進本地債券市場進一步同埋持續發展。
去年中，會唔會通過法例為伊斯蘭債券提供一個與傳統債券相若嘅税務架構，提供公平嘅税務環境，令使使香港發展伊斯蘭債券市場嘅競爭力得以提升？
為咗維持呢一方面嘅穩步發展，我哋認為政府債券計劃應可按市場情況及需要發行伊斯蘭債券。
呢個可以讓市場認識到本港嘅監管同埋税務架構均十分完備，足以支持發行伊斯蘭債券，並可藉此進一步鼓勵其他有意發行伊斯蘭債券嘅本地及國際嘅公司型發債人來港集資。
主席有別於喺政府債券計劃下發行嘅傳統政府債券，伊斯蘭債券嘅結構係按符合伊斯蘭律法嘅原則設計，涉及設立特定目的工具同埋資產轉移，因此我哋建議修訂借款條例。
把政府發行伊斯蘭債券嘅情況視為條例所指嘅借入款項。
使政府債券計劃可發行伊斯蘭債券。
香港與我哋，我哋與香港金融管理局，即係金管局，正研究有關細節，以便在條例草案獲得通過之後，視乎情市場情況，制定落實發行伊斯蘭債券嘅具體方案。
按照我哋初步嘅構思，政府嘅債券計劃下首度發行嘅伊斯蘭債券，會以本港及全球機構投資者為發行對象，並考慮以常見嘅伊斯蘭債券。
租任安排嘅形式，作為有關債券嘅結構。
除咗營造有利伊斯蘭金融發展嘅環境外，政府同埋有關機構，包括金管局、證監會同埋香港交易所，一直協力增進市場對伊斯蘭金融嘅認識同埋了解。我哋亦透過鞏固香港與主要伊斯蘭金融市場，
嘅聯繫同埋鼓勵產品嘅開發。
促進伊斯蘭金融嘅發展。
例如，金管局與馬來西亞中央銀行喺去年成立咗一個由私營機構主導嘅。
伊斯蘭金融合作小組為兩地嘅市場人士提供一個平台，以便雙方討論伊斯蘭金融嘅實務同埋相關事宜，嚟推動兩地私營機構更緊密嘅合作。
另外，證監會亦與馬來西亞證監會喺二零零九年簽署。
互相合作發展伊斯蘭資本市場及伊斯蘭集體投資計劃嘅聲明，為互相認可受予公眾嘅伊斯蘭集體投資計劃定立框架。
正如我哋喺法案委員會嘅會議上指出。
過去數年，政府同埋有關機構一直向國際投資者宣傳香港作為國際金融中心所具備嘅優點同埋商機。
本地嘅債券市場同埋我哋上市平台嘅優勢，係我哋向國際投資者宣傳嘅重點之一。
日後我哋會繼續把握機會，向機構投資者。
發債人同埋資產管理經理推介香港嘅債券市場，包括伊斯蘭債券市場。
正如今年嘅財政預算案指出，喺條例草案通過後，喺政府債券計劃下首度發行伊斯蘭債券，將會提供一個好機會，讓政府當局向國際市場展示香港伊斯蘭金融平台嘅優勢，而帶動更多發債人透過香港嘅金融市場。
集資。
由於香港政府擁有優良嘅信貸評級，我哋預我哋預期，日後推廣香港首度發行嘅政府伊斯蘭債券，會受國際及本地投資者關注，提高香港喺國際伊斯蘭伊斯蘭金融市場上嘅知名度同埋地位。
我哋會繼續聯合監管機構、駐外經貿辦事處同埋其他相關組織，積極咁向外國際投資者宣傳香港作為國際金融中心所具備嘅優點同埋商機。
主席，我希望本會能夠支持條例草案，使政府債券計劃可發行伊斯蘭債券，推動伊斯蘭金融嘅發展，從而鞏固香港嘅國際金融中心及資產管理中心嘅地位。多謝主席。
現在我提出嘅代決議題係二零一四年借款修訂條例草案予以議讀，咁現在付諸表決，贊成嘅請舉手。
反對嘅請舉手。我認為議題獲得在席議員以過半數贊成，我宣佈議案獲得通過。二零一四年借款修訂條例草案。
全體委員會審議階段，本會現在成為全體委員會。現在各位提出嘅代議議題係以下條文納入二零一四年借款修訂條例草案。
第一至九條，有冇委員要發言？
噉我現仲有各位提出上述代決議題，附諸表決，贊成嘅請舉手。
反對嘅請舉手。我認為議題獲得在席委員以過半數贊成，我宣佈議案獲得通過。全體委員會現在回覆為立法會三讀《二零一四年借款修訂條例草案》。財經事務及庫務局局長。
主席，二零一四年借款修訂條例草案。
無經修正，已通過全體委員會審議階段。
我動議此條例草案於二三讀並通過。現場各位提出嘅代議議題係二零一四年借款修訂條例草案，予以三讀並通過。有冇議員要發言？
現在我喺提出上述代決議題，付諸表決，贊成嘅請舉手。
反對嘅請舉手。
我認為議題獲得在席議員以過半數贊成，我宣佈議案獲得通過。
二零一四年借款修訂條例草案。